The idea behind the Stuxnet computer worm
ان الفكرة من وراء دودة ستوكسنت الحاسوبية
is actually quite simple.
هي بسيطةٌ جداً
We don't want Iran to get the bomb.
ان لا تحصل إيران على القنبلة النووية
Their major asset for developing nuclear weapons
ان المكان الاساسي الذي من المفترض ان يتم فيه تطوير الاسلحة النووية
is the Natanz uranium enrichment facility.
هو منشأة تخصيب اليورانيوم في منطقة " ناتنز "
The gray boxes that you see,
ان العلب الرمادية التي ترونها هنا
these are real-time control systems.
انها عبارة عن انظمة تحكم
Now if we manage to compromise these systems
وان استطعت ان تخرب هذه الانظمة
that control drive speeds and valves,
والتي تتحكم بسرعة و حركة الصمامات
we can actually cause a lot of problems
يمكن ان تسبب الكثير من المشاكل
with the centrifuge.
في اجهزة الطرد المركزي
The gray boxes don't run Windows software;
ان هذه العلب الرمادية لا تعمل حتماً على نظام ويندوز
they are a completely different technology.
انها تعمل على نظام مختلف جداً
But if we manage
ولكن ان استطعنا ..
to place a good Windows virus
ان نضع فيروس يهاجم نظام ويندوز
on a notebook
على جهاز اللابتوب
that is used by a maintenance engineer
الذي يستخدمه مهندسو ذلك الجهاز
to configure this gray box,
لضبط ذلك الجهاز
then we are in business.
فسنستطيع اختراقه
And this is the plot behind Stuxnet.
وهذه هي فكرة دودة ستوكسنت الالكترونية
So we start with a Windows dropper.
كل ما نحتاجه نظام ويندوز يحوي الدودة
The payload goes onto the gray box,
ومن ثم يتم تحميله على الاجهزة الرمادية
damages the centrifuge,
لتعطيل اجهزة الطرد المركزي
and the Iranian nuclear program is delayed --
فيتأخر برنامج إيران النووي
mission accomplished.
وتنجح المهمة
That's easy, huh?
يبدو الامر سهلاً .. أليس كذلك ؟
I want to tell you how we found that out.
سأخبركم كيف استطعنا ان نكتشف هذه الدودة الالكترونية
When we started our research on Stuxnet six months ago,
عندما بدأنا البحث فيما يخص ستوكسنت منذ 6 اشهر
it was completely unknown what the purpose of this thing was.
كان الهدف الذي تستهدفه هذه الدودة مجهول تماما بالنسبة لنا
The only thing that was known
والشيء الوحيد الذي كنا نعيه ..
is it's very, very complex on the Windows part, the dropper part,
هو ان هذه الدودة تختبىء في جزء معقد جداً من نظام ويندوز وتستخدمه كناقل
used multiple zero-day vulnerabilities.
وتستخدم عدة نقاط ضعف في النظام لاختراقه
And it seemed to want to do something
وكان جلياً بالنسبة لنا انها - الدودة الالكترونية - تحاول القيام بشيء ما
with these gray boxes, these real-time control systems.
بخصوص هذه العلب الرمادية .. علب التحكم
So that got our attention,
وهذا ما جذب اهتمامنا ..
and we started a lab project
وقد بدأنا البحث المخبري
where we infected our environment with Stuxnet
حيث اطلقنا دودة ستوكسنت في انظمتنا
and checked this thing out.
اخذنا نراقب التبعات جراء ذلك
And then some very funny things happened.
وقد لاحظنا شيئاً مضحكاً ..
Stuxnet behaved like a lab rat
ان دودة ستوكسنت كانت تتصرف كـ فأر المختبر
that didn't like our cheese --
الذي لا يحب الجبنة التي نقدمها له ..
sniffed, but didn't want to eat.
كان يشتم هذه الجبنة .. ولكنه لا يأكلها
Didn't make sense to me.
لم يكن ذلك منطقيا بالنسبة لنا
And after we experimented with different flavors of cheese,
وبعد عدة نكهات من الجبن التي قدمناها للدودة - عدة انظمة -
I realized, well, this is a directed attack.
لاحظنا .. ان هذه الدودة ليست دودة هجوم عشوائية بل موجهة
It's completely directed.
موجهة تحديداً لهدف ما ..
The dropper is prowling actively
انها موجهة تماماً
on the gray box
تجاه العلب الرمادية
if a specific configuration is found,
وحتى ان وجدت هذه الدودة الانظمة المستهدفة ..
and even if the actual program code that it's trying to infect
فإن لم يكن هذا النظام يعمل بصورة واقعية
is actually running on that target.
ويعمل على اجهزة الطرد المركزي
And if not, Stuxnet does nothing.
فإن دودة ستوكسنت لن تقوم بشيء ما
So that really got my attention,
وهذا فعلاً قد جذب اهتمامي
and we started to work on this
وقد بدأنا العمل على هذا الامر لفهم ماهيته
nearly around the clock,
على مدار الساعة
because I thought, "Well, we don't know what the target is.
لاننا لم نكن نعرف ما هو الهدف
It could be, let's say for example,
فهو يمكن ان يكون .. على سبيل المثال
a U.S. power plant,
مصنع طاقة في الولايات المتحدة
or a chemical plant in Germany.
او مصنع كيميائي في ألمانيا
So we better find out what the target is soon."
لذا كان يتوجب علينا ان نعرف ما هو الهدف باسرع وقت ممكن
So we extracted and decompiled
لذا قمنا بفكه .. فرزه .. وقراءة برمجيته
the attack code,
وتحديداً كود الهجوم
and we discovered that it's structured in two digital bombs --
ولقد وجدنا انه مبرمج على نظامي هجوم - قنبلتين رقميتين -
a smaller one and a bigger one.
واحدة صغيرة .. وأخرى كبيرة
And we also saw that they are very professionally engineered
ولقد أدركنا على الفور انها - الدودة - مبرمجة بصورة عالية الاحتراف والتقنية
by people who obviously had all insider information.
بواسطة اشخاص لديهم كل المعلومات الكافية والوافية عن الهدف
They knew all the bits and bites
فقد تعرفوا كل " البيتات " الموجودة في برمجية الهدف
that they had to attack.
والتي يجب ان تُهاجم
They probably even know the shoe size of the operator.
ربما كانوا يعرفون حتى مقاس حذاء مشغل الجهاز
So they know everything.
إذا لقد كانوا يعلمون كل شيء
And if you have heard that the dropper of Stuxnet
وان كنتم سمعتم ان دودة ستوكسنت وطريقة توجهها ودخولها الى النظام
is complex and high-tech,
هي معقدة وعالية التقنية
let me tell you this:
دعوني اخبركم
the payload is rocket science.
ان طريقة " تحميل الدودة الى الجهاز " تفوق برمجة الصواريخ
It's way above everything
انها متقدمة جداً اكثر من اي شيء
that we have ever seen before.
انها برمجية لم نرى مثيلاً لها من ذي قبل
Here you see a sample of this actual attack code.
سوف اريكم جزء من برمجية الهجوم
We are talking about --
نحن هنا نتحدث
around about 15,000 lines of code.
عن ما يقارب 1500 سطر من البرمجية الكلية
Looks pretty much like old-style assembly language.
تبدو تماما مثل لغة التجميع القديمة
And I want to tell you how we were able
واريد ان اخبركم كيف استطعنا ان نفك شيفرة
to make sense out of this code.
هذه البرمجية
So what we were looking for is, first of all, system function calls,
بداية كنا نبحث عن الدوال
because we know what they do.
لاننا كنا نعرف انها " الموجهات "
And then we were looking for timers and data structures
ومن ثم بدأنا نبحث عن العدادات .. وانظمة المعلومات
and trying to relate them to the real world --
وحاولنا ان نصل بين تلك المعلومات وبين الاهداف ..
to potential real world targets.
التي افترضناها من الواقع
So we do need target theories
لذا كنا نفترض مجموعة اهداف
that we can prove or disprove.
ونقوم بفحص الشيفرة هل موافقة ام لا
In order to get target theories,
ولكي نمايز بين فرضيات الاهداف
we remember
وضعنا نصب اعيُننا
that it's definitely hardcore sabotage,
ان الهدف من عملية التخريب هذه
it must be a high-value target
يجب ان يكون هدفاً عالي القيمة جداً
and it is most likely located in Iran,
وهو على الاغلب موجود في إيران
because that's where most of the infections had been reported.
لان معظم الاصابات بهذه الدودة بلغ عنها من تلك المنطقة
Now you don't find several thousand targets in that area.
وحتماً لا توجد في تلك المنطقة .. العديد من الاهداف
It basically boils down
وفي النهاية قلصت الاهداف المحتملة
to the Bushehr nuclear power plant
الى مجمع بوشهر النووي
and to the Natanz fuel enrichment plant.
ومركز تخصيب اليورانيوم في " نتناز "
So I told my assistant,
لذا اخبرت مساعدي ..
"Get me a list of all centrifuge and power plant experts from our client base."
أحضر لي قائمة بالخبراء باجهزة الطرد المركزي والطاقة من مركز معلوماتنا "
And I phoned them up and picked their brain
من ثم بدأنا بالاتصال بهم
in an effort to match their expertise
لكي نوفق بين ما وجدناه
with what we found in code and data.
وبين ما هو موجود في معلومات وكودات التي يعمل عليها هؤلاء الخبراء
And that worked pretty well.
وقد نجحنا بذلك
So we were able to associate
لقد وجدنا الرابط
the small digital warhead
انه رقم صغير يعمل كرأس حربي
with the rotor control.
يهاجم برمجية تتحكم بعنفة
The rotor is that moving part within the centrifuge,
تدور في نظام الطرد المركزي
that black object that you see.
العنصر الاسود الذي ترونه هنا
And if you manipulate the speed of this rotor,
وان استطعت ان تغير او تتلاعب بسرعة هذه العنفة
you are actually able to crack the rotor
يمكنك ان تدمرها
and eventually even have the centrifuge explode.
وهذا سيؤدي في النهاية الى تدمير \ انفجار اجهزة الطرد المركزي
What we also saw
وما لاحظناه أيضاً
is that the goal of the attack
ان الهدف من الهجوم
was really to do it slowly and creepy --
هو ان يتم بصورة بطيئة و مخادعة
obviously in an effort
بهدف
to drive maintenance engineers crazy,
جعل عمال الصيانة يصابون بالجنون
that they would not be able to figure this out quickly.
وان لا يستطيعوا ان يميزوا المشكلة بسرعة
The big digital warhead -- we had a shot at this
اما برمجية الهجوم الاكبر
by looking very closely
بعد النظر اليها جيداً
at data and data structures.
على برمجيتها و هيكليتها
So for example, the number 164
وجدنا رقم غريب هو 164
really stands out in that code;
كان جليٌ لنا انه مميز
you can't overlook it.
ولم نستطع ان نتجاهله
I started to research scientific literature
بدأنا نبحث في المحاضرات العلمية
on how these centrifuges
عن كيفية عمل أجهزة الطرد المركزي
are actually built in Natanz
والتي كانت مبنية في منشأة نتناز
and found they are structured
ولقد وجدنا انها مرتبة
in what is called a cascade,
بشكل متتالي
and each cascade holds 164 centrifuges.
وكل متتالية تحتوي على 164 من اجهزة الطرد المركزي
So that made sense, that was a match.
وكان هذا التوافق الاكبر الذي وجدناه
And it even got better.
ولكن الامور تغدو أكثر إثارة
These centrifuges in Iran
فأجهزة الطرد المركزي في إيران
are subdivided into 15, what is called, stages.
مقسومة الى 15 .. يمكن ان نقول 15 مرحلة
And guess what we found in the attack code?
وتوقعوا مالذي وجدناه في شيفرة الهجوم ؟
An almost identical structure.
تطابقٌ تام
So again, that was a real good match.
مرة أخرى .. كان التطابق واضحٌ جداً
And this gave us very high confidence for what we were looking at.
وقد اعطانا ثقة تامة بأن هذا هو ما نبحث عنه
Now don't get me wrong here, it didn't go like this.
الان لا تفهموني بصورة خاطئة .. ان الامر ليس بهذه السهولة
These results have been obtained
لقد حصلنا على هذه النتائج
over several weeks of really hard labor.
بعد عدة اسابيع من العمل المضني
And we often went into just a dead end
وبعد ان وصلنا الى عدة نهايات مغلقة
and had to recover.
وكان علينا البدء من جديد مرة اخرى
Anyway, so we figured out
حسناً .. لقد اكتشفنا إذا
that both digital warheads
ان شيفرتي الهجوم
were actually aiming at one and the same target,
كانتا تستهدفان نفس الهدف
but from different angles.
كل من زواية خاصة به
The small warhead is taking one cascade,
حيث تهاجم الاولى الصغيرة احد الشلالات " التي تتوزع فيها اجهزة الطرد "
and spinning up the rotors and slowing them down,
ويحاول ان يعبث بالعنفة و يقلل من سرعتها
and the big warhead
والثانية الكبيرة
is talking to six cascades
تهاجم المتتاليات الست
and manipulating valves.
وتتلاعب بالصمامات
So in all, we are very confident
لقد كنا واثقين جداً
that we have actually determined what the target is.
اننا قد عرفنا الهدف بصورة لا مجال للشك فيها
It is Natanz, and it is only Natanz.
انه في نتناز .. نتناز وحدها
So we don't have to worry
لذا لم يكن يتوجب علينا ان نقلق
that other targets
من وجود اهداف اخرى
might be hit by Stuxnet.
ربما قد تُضرب بواسطة دودة ستوكسنت
Here's some very cool stuff that we saw --
وهناك شيء رائع مبدع وجدناه ايضاً
really knocked my socks off.
أطار لنا عقولنا من شدة إبداعه
Down there is the gray box,
في الاسفل ترون العلب الرمادية
and on the top you see the centrifuges.
وهناك في الاعلى ترون اجهزة الطرد المركزي
Now what this thing does
حسناً .. ماذا يفعل هذا الشيء ..
is it intercepts the input values from sensors --
انه يقوم باعتراض المعلومات التي تصدر من مجسات الصمامات
so for example, from pressure sensors
على سبيل المثال مجسات الضغط
and vibration sensors --
او مجسات الاهتزاز
and it provides legitimate program code,
ومن ثم يقوم تبعاً لبرمجية معينة
which is still running during the attack,
والتي تعمل أثناء الهجوم
with fake input data.
بإستبدال البيانات ببيانات خاطئة
And as a matter of fact, this fake input data
و في الحقيقة، إدخال بيانات وهمية
is actually prerecorded by Stuxnet.
تقوم دودة ستوكسنت بتسجيلها مسبقاً من نفس المجسات
So it's just like from the Hollywood movies
كما في افلام هوليود
where during the heist,
حيث أثناء سرقة،
the observation camera is fed with prerecorded video.
تقوم كاميرة المراقبة بعرض فلم مسبق التسجيل للموقع حتى لا يبدو هناك شيءٌ ما
That's cool, huh?
أمرٌ رائع .. أليس كذلك ؟
The idea here is obviously
الفكرة ليست فحسب
not only to fool the operators in the control room.
مخادعة للقائمين على المنشأة
It actually is much more dangerous and aggressive.
بل اكثر من هذا عدواة وخطورة ..
The idea
الفكرة
is to circumvent a digital safety system.
هي مخادعة أنظمة الامان الإلكترونية
We need digital safety systems
نحن عادة نحتاج انظمة الآمان الإلكترونية
where a human operator could not act quick enough.
لكي تتصرف أسرع من الانسان لمواكبة للأخطار
So for example, in a power plant,
فعلى سبير المثال في محطات الطاقة
when your big steam turbine gets too over speed,
عندما يقوم توربين بخاري بالدوران بسرعة اكبر من اللازم
you must open relief valves within a millisecond.
يجب على الفور وخلال جزء من الثانية ان يتم فتح صمامات الامان
Obviously, this cannot be done by a human operator.
وحتماً هذا لا يمكن القيام به بواسطة البشر
So this is where we need digital safety systems.
لهذا نحتاج أنظمة الآمان الإلكترونية
And when they are compromised,
وعندما يتم " مخادعتها \ التحايل عليها "
then real bad things can happen.
فإن مخاطر جمة قد تحدث ..
Your plant can blow up.
مثل انفجار المعمل \ المنشأة
And neither your operators nor your safety system will notice it.
والمشكلة ان لا مراقب المعمل ولا نظام الآمان سوف يلحظ هذا ..
That's scary.
ان هذا خطرٌ جداً
But it gets worse.
والامر يزداد سوءاً
And this is very important, what I'm going to say.
وهذا أمرٌ مهم جداً .. واريدكم
Think about this:
ان تفكروا بهذا
this attack is generic.
تصورا هذا الهجوم بصورة عامة ..
It doesn't have anything to do, in specifics,
تصوروا .. ان لايكون الامر
with centrifuges,
متعلق بأجهزة الطرد المركزي
with uranium enrichment.
او بتخصيب اليورانيوم
So it would work as well, for example,
لان هذه الدودة قد تعمل بصورة ممتازة
in a power plant
على مصانع الطاقة
or in an automobile factory.
او مصانع السيارات
It is generic.
انها دودة تصيب كل شيء
And you don't have -- as an attacker --
وانت - كمهاجم -
you don't have to deliver this payload
لا يتوجب عليك ان تحمل هذه الدودة مباشرة
by a USB stick,
بواسطة " USB "
as we saw it in the case of Stuxnet.
كما رأينا في حالة دودة ستوكسنت الإلكترونية
You could also use conventional worm technology for spreading.
كل ما تريده هو ان تنشر هذه الدودة في فضاء الانترنت
Just spread it as wide as possible.
ان تنشرها بالقدر الكافي
And if you do that,
وان استطعت ان تقوم بهذا
what you end up with
سوف تحصل في النهاية
is a cyber weapon of mass destruction.
على سلاح دمار شامل " إلكتروني "
That's the consequence
ان عواقب هذا
that we have to face.
هو ما سنواجهه في المستقبل
So unfortunately,
ولسوء الحظ ..
the biggest number of targets for such attacks
ان الاهداف الاكبر لهكذا " برمجيات "
are not in the Middle East.
ليست في الشرق الاوسط
They're in the United States and Europe and in Japan.
انما هي في الولايات المتحدة .. والاتحاد الاوروبي .. وفي اليابان
So all of the green areas,
وكل تلك المناطق " الخضراء "
these are your target-rich environments.
التي هي غنية بالاهداف عالية التقنية .. !
We have to face the consequences,
علينا ان نواجه عواقب هذا في المستقبل
and we better start to prepare right now.
والافضل ان نبدأ بالاستعداد الآن
Thanks.
شُكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: I've got a question.
كريس أندرسون : لدي تساؤل
Ralph, it's been quite widely reported
رالف .. هناك الكثير من التقارير التي
that people assume that Mossad
تقول ان " المُوساد الإسرائيلي "
is the main entity behind this.
وراء هذه الدودة
Is that your opinion?
هل هذا هو رأيك ؟
Ralph Langner: Okay, you really want to hear that?
رالف لانجير : حسناً .. هل تريد حقاً معرفة وجهة نظري ؟
Yeah. Okay.
حسناً .. نعم
My opinion is that the Mossad is involved,
ان رأي هو ان المُساد مشارك بهذه الدودة
but that the leading force is not Israel.
ولكن .. القوى العظمى في هذا الخصوص .. ليست إسرائيل
So the leading force behind that
ان القوى المحركة لهذه الدودة ..
is the cyber superpower.
هي قوى عظمى إلكترونياً
There is only one,
وهناك قوة واحدة فحسب في هذا العالم
and that's the United States --
وهي الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
fortunately, fortunately.
وهذا لحسن .. الحظ .. نعم لحسن الحظ
Because otherwise,
لانه لو كان الامر غير هذا
our problems would even be bigger.
فإن مشاكلنا سوف تكون أكبر مما يمكن تخيله
CA: Thank you for scaring the living daylights out of us. Thank you, Ralph.
كيس آندرسون : شكراً لإخافتنا رالف .. شكراً لك
(Applause)
(تصفيق)